we're tracking tracking tracking
tracking he I was just thinking that the
the song mask off by future is gonna
just come
be super popular again yeah like we will
it'll probably become the number-one hit
when all this blows over but I mean I
guess the course is about Molly's and
percocets
but mask off will be an appropriate term
we were talking about how it's like we
both have our own versions of masks
right now we're at with the Cova thing
but it might be like a super normal
thing for all of America to just be
wearing masks in one month it'll be the
latest fashion accessory yeah you'll be
seeing you know the I mean there already
are babe and off-white because of Asia
but you'll be seeing the Gucci and Louis
Vuitton and the yes all those brands
making I have I have like these the
Amazon knockoff version of something
that looks like the target version of
babe so I'm a few levels down but I
luckily a much as much of a street where
F boy that I have it's not it's not babe
spelled BAE P like you'd get I thought
it was babe well no like it is babe it's
be ap not be a EP oh right yeah yeah
yeah it's a babe is actually it's
bathing ape unit a bathe a bathing ape
yeah what an interesting thing that's
like one of the more popular brands and
that's their name I mean good on them oh
yeah I mean and then they have baby Milo
the there's a little mascot isn't that
what it's called the the kids store is
is they have do we live in a video game
is this i I don't I don't know might we
might live in a video game and I think
so I'm all aboard it feels like a video
game lately cuz so what are we doing
right now we are at there's a courting
studio we are we're at Black Diamond
recording studios in Portland Oregon yes
we are doing a socially distant yet not
podcast experience yes
because it's more fun to be doing this
in person than over shitty webcam and
when you're in recording studio and
you're using a core webcam microphone
that does not it doesn't equate well at
all to what we are and what we're
capable of doing yeah so what this one
has to be impressive it has to be
impressive and if you're not impressed
by the sound quality you can be
impressed by the content of what we're
about to be talking about oh man now
there's a lot of pressure so much I
don't know we're just gonna get ready to
disappoint okay here comes the
disappointment all right that's it for
see you later
goodbye have a good night No so this
this is cool that we're doing this it's
just like it's it's such a weird time
that's like what we've been talking
about the last hour is just it's a
confusing weird time it's hard to know
what to do and how to do it in like when
you email people right now it seems
different and weird when you text people
it seems different than weird like
conducting businesses we are driving is
where everything is just supervise
everything is it's changed I had I had
to take my dog to the vet and and you
drop it drop the animal off and it's
curbside pickup for your vet appointment
it seems brutal yeah it's weird
yeah that's like the drive-in vet yeah
you go out honey you're fine yeah it's
like here here go make some friends go
with the stranger I'm just gonna hand
you out the car window and yeah see you
in a bit what what others should do you
think is gonna be but what other [__] is
different what other stuff have you
experienced that's different so far mmm
not being able to I mean not being able
to like just go out and go like shopping
or browsing or like anything like Helms
like I live in downtown so just walking
around downtown like you can still go
out and walk but it's desolate do you
feel like you're breaking the law when
you're out walking no more than I
normally do breaking the law yeah I was
we were at a we went to Fred Meyer like
to go shopping and that didn't seem
super weird like it is weird seeing the
empty shelves but then just kind of out
of habit we got to where it starts like
had they have clothes and furniture and
we're like and we're just like kind of
walking down that way and we're like ah
wait well thought this feels weird let's
turn around and just go home yeah it's
like it's like why we don't need to be
going and going shopping at IKEA right
like that we don't we don't need a
detail well although a lot of people are
probably going shopping at IKEA to get
some desks to assembly and there yeah
home offices some standup desks and all
that other yes everyone's working from
home working from home less you're one
of the lucky few who isn't who isn't
well so working in solitude and like
introverted style of working as
something that you know very well yeah I
know I know pretty well myself so how
has how is like work changed for you
lately and actually we can probably
bring that right into kind of an
introduction maybe give a little bit of
your background if you'd like to so they
know who they're talking to
sure seamless seamless seamless seamless
they won't even suspect it they probably
won't no not at all we didn't just have
a complete technical malfunction we've
never had one in her life no not at all
engineers are perfect yep let's see
alright so the video is recording video
part 2 so now you'll you'll be able to
you know edit it all together and all
that stuff cuz you know we didn't have
any technical difficulties and I'm going
to continually make sure that we don't
have any more technical difficulties
just have a little glance Mac ones yeah
just a little glance Ipoh here there so
back to solitary confinement and living
a life of loneliness and computers in
despair and despair because that's what
we were talking about so working in
solitude is nice actually now we've been
we've been trying to stay relatively
busy I have a lot of remote remote work
and stuff that I have to have to do
which is nice with
my clients but aside from that it's it's
pretty much very like slow yeah yeah cuz
I'll be slow and it's just weird
it's just weird it's just like what like
we're waiting for whatever we're
supposed to be doing next but we still
don't really know what that's going to
be so it's hard to prepare for it at the
same time yup it's weird it's weird cuz
no one knows exactly what's gonna be
happening in a month from now I mean you
know shows are cancelled bars are
cancelled strip clubs are cancelled
cancelled cancelled Coachella's
postponed Coachella is cancelled
crumbles on ground and cries actually I
did enjoy Coachella I've been a couple
times it is fun but I don't think they
don't you know again I don't I don't
know after this whole thing yeah it's
just that's that's the other thing is
like our people it's you're gonna go to
a music festival and everyone's gonna
have like a lot of space in between each
other can I mean that sounds actually
really nice ma what what is a mosh pit
we just bring back we'd have amps guard
here allowed those the totems like ECAM
totems but you can bring your amps guard
weapons you get the moshing oh man that
would be actually so cool like imagine
if you're listening to your favorite
artists but you also get to just beat
the crap out of people you don't know
with like it's LARPing but replacing the
market so working in quarantine I don't
think we got your background on this
take so do you want to provide they
listeners with a bit of your background
my my name is Andy
i'ma recording engineer and music
producer and geek nerd weird oh I work
at Black Diamond recording studios in
Portland Oregon I've been doing it for
about 7 years here but doing audio stuff
since I was like 10
and yeah that pretty much sums up my
life story
see yeah that's it that's it for
listening see you later now you know
everything about me
yep okay going back to when you were 10
years old what what first kind of like
got you interested in all this stuff it
probably have to be when I was messing
around with my dad's old hi-fi and
reel-to-reel tape machine and that kind
of stuff we would spend hours tracking
vinyls to cassettes because that was the
way to listen to music at the time you
didn't have Spotify oh yeah Spotify in
the 90s the early 90s yeah the only
green logo was was LimeWire was LimeWire
even though yeah
she's white - yeah I think that was
LimeWire was like I was in - why high
school middle school so yeah like early
2000s right so you were like 19 like I
want to say LimeWire was probably like
99 2000 2001 that generation yeah I feel
like it was right around that within
those three years was definitely like
the peak LimeWire yeah I would bet my
the will of my dog and what was DC plus
plus his net what else were there those
were so like let all seek soul Sica
still a thing where the rest of these
places I'm not promoting piracy we don't
condone that on this radio program here
I remember I've never pirated a thing in
my life you know we're not DJs we've
never downloaded a song off the the
Napster's what do deejays even do who
have never was none of those mp3s that
people talk about we get everything on
the classic CD from the local Walmart
yeah we buy so that's what a DJ does if
you didn't know listener if they go down
to Walmart and they get the edited
version sometimes sometimes not and they
burn it to their CD player and then on
to their computer after the CD player
and then and there's a huge step process
you know where it hits the computer you
got to make sure it's clean duty
nowadays though is so weird if you think
about it I might be I'm rubbing against
that hardcore it's it's just an insane
thing cuz for one of my gigs you have to
you have to do like ultra school clean
and so you can't dip into like it yes
it's not explicit does have cuss words
but it's just saying vulgar crazy [__]
that you can't hear oh yeah it's it when
people ask me for a clean version of a
song I'm sitting there like oh [__]
there's a lot words that you say that
they're questionable and like themes too
not just words it's like themes it's
like I mean you technically didn't cuss
but like but you said it's sucking on my
yeah so I don't know if you can talk
about is there anything since sucking on
that's like school appropriate to say I
don't think so even sucking on a
lollipop will be taken wrong it's a
weird world I wonder if I kind of like
revamp cuss words at some point they've
got it like we're just ignoring the fact
that cuss words have just evolved into
cooler crazy full sentences now yeah and
there's so many like nuances behind like
[__] when you say [__] there's just it's
a nuanced word it's it's it's it should
be okay to say there's so many layers to
it I know and it's it seems like
depending on where you go like people
will give a [__] about one thing and not
give a [__] about another like you go go
to Australia and you're up and [__] and
they're like oh yeah
you can say whatever the [__] you want
on TVs think about [__] - the word [__]
yeah like around here it makes like a
lot of people listening probably got
super uncomfortable they're just like
what and we're like it's the British
we're talk about the British meaning
yeah did you not hear my yeah my British
yeah he's not sound like the British
version I don't know it just it sounded
like you might have said cheeky [__] but
maybe you've met the American one and it
was like a weird weird insult but I
don't I don't know humans are so simple
in complex in the same exact way because
of situations like that why can't we all
just be like oh okay they say it over
there and it doesn't hurt anybody why
don't we just listen why does it hurt
people here I mean there's certain
things that yes it's nuanced that you
definitely don't want to talk about but
then there's other things where it's
like yeah that's a cuss word that what
yeah like who said that that's a bad way
okay I guess we gotta follow those rules
yeah especially like with with songs and
art and that kind of thing that's just
kind of like okay I remember I had to DJ
for a event in Utah and it had to be in
an entirely clean DJ set do you know how
hard that [__] is I do I do that a
lot but it's different tough it's hard
and like you're even like going back to
like all these some oldies you're like
this is kind of questionable what
they're talking about they're using like
weird words like oh like a chubby
Whoopi's and stuff and you're like it's
trouble you always mad can i dad are
like subject matter it's like this is
real creeper like talking about having a
girl like kissing you on the hand and
all this other [__] you're like hell lay
[__] like how old is the girl in this
song yeah like what's his name [__]
uh Conway Twitty that dude dude all of
his songs are just the like they don't
age well at all like yikes
yeah it's it's pretty gnarly it's pretty
not there's a lot of music that's not
like really gonna age well do you do you
remember can you think back to your
first gig like audio anything was it DJ
gig was that your first gig Oh like like
paying gig or first gig because there's
we got to hear both because if you
volunteered for your first one first
first one first technical one was
running the sound board for my middle
school at some sort of events that was
like the like I was probably what 11 ish
was like the first like this is a job
you have to perform then it's not just
[__] around with stuff and that was
pretty probably the first gig
quote-on-quote that I had to do my first
paying one was I was DJing a friend's
house party and he ended up paying me
for it because the night went well
mm-hmm held Rhea you remember I was
under 18 1516
yeah yeah I was like I think I was 16
you remember what you played dude it was
2004 five so lots of like early French
house stuff like justice and Daft Punk
and mmhmm like yeah like I think it was
yeah that was around the time I think I
think just that justice that either just
released we are your friends or it was a
right before that whole blog house
started coming up yeah I was like FX
twin dong I couldn't like a bunch of
house artists that I'm trying to
remember but they're like a lot of
one-offs I had a lot of vinyl and they
were like from house labels that may or
may not still exist so did you bring
your crates and everything what was your
setup oh yeah I had like I had my very
first DJ set up that was like a proper
DJ setup was to Denon DNS 1000s which I
still own and then the mixer the tiny
little mixer and then is it that
thousand or one hundred I don't remember
these tiny little CDJs that words they
were they did the job yet they they
weren't fancy at all and then I had some
Staunton turntables good old Stan belt
driven turntables and those are what I
learned to be match on which were
horrible to learn on they were the worst
till [__] learn how to beat match on
don't if you ever want to learn how to
spin vinyl don't use belt driven
turntables get direct drive technics are
similar yes you will have a bad time
yeah I don't even know how to like like
I've been a DJ for so many years but
it's such a different time and it's such
like a different corner of DJing like
because there's so many different facets
of DJing oh yeah like you have your your
what your festival DJ your I hope your
bedroom DJ your club DJ that's like the
weekend warrior club DJ you yes you know
that laughs anyway
that library not lately though yeah same
I've been there done that
um and then you have like the wedding DJ
you also know that very well
what else the the turntable is table
lists and then you have like the the
radio DJ typical more like an emcee at
that point right some are still
technically disc jockeys and then you
have like the producer who then becomes
a DJ who sucks the DJing right yes I was
talking about that I had mr. Carmack
like I love that dude he's such a Geo
mr. cravaack is yeah yeah he's a couple
thing man he's I really like his stuff
he's very original when like I really
like him as a producer but uh I don't
know I remember maybe it was just the
experience that I had one or two
experiences that festivals were he just
like like mixing between two songs
sounded really mad for whatever reason
I'm like man you shit's so good just
take a little extra time and learn to
actually DJ it but yeah it could have
been the one-off festivals there's a
there's a lot of that that I've seen I
mean like a great counter to that in
like Calvin Harris isn't really [__]
awesome DJ and a really good producer
and then you have like people like
Tiesto who at one point I think produced
his music maybe not as much anymore I
don't know
there's Tiesto a construct I made
possibly he's just like what is it he's
just like slash it's just a figment of
the imagination okay he could be I've
seen him a couple times I think that
every time I've seen Tiesto it's been
quite an enjoyable set but I think that
I was in the situation just like he's
he's a decent DJ right I just its
productions have been varied over the
years right he's like a whole brand like
a whole well he was he was the
highest-paid DJ in the world for many
moons right see that's until a certain
point
that's so weird to think about because
highest-paid DJ like that word is just
used for 70 million things yeah yeah
I've been a producer yeah
think it was like he was the
highest-paid disc jockey who's like the
touring kind of almost festival like
because I mean like he always has those
giant ass shows in Amsterdam and Europe
and like all the big gas techno shows
and stuff like that it's a damn good
time oh yeah I'm [__] I really wanted
to go to one of those but hey no that'll
be yeah it might be another six months
before we're allowed 50 people at a time
in one place glorious
so we'll see about that okay so from
your first show what was your DJ life
unfolding like after like the next
couple years
you were 20s or so area
what did life lead you did - Japan moved
to Japan helped a lot because you know
they don't card so I was like 18 years
17 18 I was no I was 18
yeah I was 18 years old working at a
couple bars and nightclubs DJing like
regularly and it was like it was a
college town so they have active
nightlife and active thing and because I
was like one of the foreigner DJ's I was
playing the music that you know wasn't
the most like popular yet I should say
because it seemed like everything in pop
culture in the West was still a little
bit of a delay like even though we had
the internet and all that other stuff it
still was like to keep to reach the
masses to where it's like oh everyone
knows this song now it'd still be like
two three months maybe right like and so
like my friend would send me a song it's
like he's like this is the banger that's
[__] happening here like what was it
it was the one that came out that I knew
was like gonna be [__] massive there
it was out in the state you uh Rihanna
umbrella they dropped that and like I
think this single came out in the States
and I heard it and I was like oh yeah
that's good that's gonna be [__]
everywhere mmm and sure enough [__]
two months later that was like the
[__] hit that's the song everyone was
requesting and all that other stuff man
Boo Radley yeah
yeah and so like it was like that was
that was a things like I would be
playing that kind of stuff compared to
the home the home town days who were and
and the other thing was I would play a
varied set and my parties are always
varied that was the one big difference
compared to like here and over there was
a lot of the clubs were very specific
genre oriented or like themed or it was
awarded they were they were the Knights
they would have specific nights for
theme night yeah theme nights but that
was the norm it wasn't and they weren't
like theme nights per se it would just
be like that's the DJ so unlike here
where you have like 80s night and like
that kinda thing where people dress up
and do all that you'd be like no it's
looks like this is the techno party
group this is the house party group
this is 90s hip-hop aficionado group
this is the like crazy reggaeton like
big speaker toting guy group which those
were actually the most fun parties
because they would like we already have
a giant sound system they would card in
the sound system like twice the size
notion tiny Club and it would just be a
wall of just bass yo it was awesome we
got so many complaints because we
weren't the only business in that
building and they would feel it those
nights like their glasses and stuff
would be shaking it would be pretty
awesome but yeah like that and I started
just DJing a bunch of different like
random part like parties at bars and
like it was a lot of really small like
dive bars and stuff like just that was
what I was playing first or the dive bar
is like way different over there oh yeah
and then here oh yeah I mean a dive bar
here like what's what do you when you
picture dive bar in Portland OR dive bar
in general dive bar to me seems more of
like kind of like an older person's
place like bikers sort of thing like I
don't know just like maybe playing that
country sort of music I think that I
would picture my head okay see so for me
a dive bar is like a tiny bar like where
it's like narrow not a lot of space
program like city block type stuff so
like like the two
or like one of those type of places in
Portland like would be to me it's like a
dive bar okay and I'd be playing a lot
of places like that but the dive bars
would be really small and I'm talking
like some one place I played at most
including myself and the bartender it
could fit like six people in a row it
was like a it was like a closet VIP yeah
and and and he just wanted me to play
some house tracks like that's it I was
like okay cool a notice one gig and then
I had I had another one where this dude
was like he was taught me and one of my
Japanese friends one of my Korean
buddies who was also there in college
with me who are all DJs they were like
he was like he booked all of us to play
this night he's like it's gonna be a
great huge party blah blah blah this no
one showed up no one showed up and I
didn't do any promoting for it cuz I was
like okay whatever if you're like you
pay me to be the DJ I'll show up and he
he had no one show up like it I was
sitting there playing to him the
bartender who looked pissed off and I
think the dudes girlfriend and so it's
like okay cool well I'm not getting paid
but I'm just gonna be playing practicing
for an hour in front of an empty room
and so like it'd be like there was a lot
but a surprising amount of gigs like
that but then I'd also have events where
if I threw one of my parties
I'd have 500 600 people and through the
night and like then when I moved back to
the states I like I was like yeah I
could I got in like met up with a couple
people who were throwing house parties
and I was like cool I want to DJ I have
a PA system and all this other stuff
already like yeah I am equipped ready
cool let's do the mobile parties let's
go and that's kind of what happened was
I would go down to Eugene and I did one
really cool block party in Corrales um
but I would go down to Eugene and up to
Portland when I moved back from Japan
and DJ college parties and stuff like
that my was it playing a lot different
music like when he came back over from
Japan like when I would play more techno
and stuff over there surprisingly no no
I got back here I started to play more
what
I wanted to play rather than playing to
a crowd playing for a crowd because when
I was playing at the club's there I
needed to keep people in the building
hmm and that's a big difference right if
I'm playing a house party I don't care
yeah if you're there like to play
whatever you want and I like my paycheck
does not depend on keeping y'all in the
building
yeah for real that kind of thing and so
that's and so I would just I started
just playing whatever I wanted and doing
my own thing and then that's when I had
my own music partner Charlie we started
team Banzai and we were doing like our
own remixes and stuff which those got
surprisingly popular and then long story
short he went off and did his own thing
and I continued on doing team bonsai
with a couple of my other buddies but
it's just a small thing now yeah not a
Mane not a main gig I can say with DJing
and production like in that realm where
it's like trying to go out and be that
DJ producer combo aware right I'm making
making all the music than playing the
live shows and doing that the touring
thing is like I like that idea but it's
also kind of like everyone and their
mothers trying to do that now right yeah
this festival DJ got the Rockstar
movement and so you get the guys like
Steve Aoki mmm DJ snake dude I just it's
a it's a circus kind of like it's a like
everybody's I called you I can get that
number one festival slaughter like
everybody's like trying to go for this
we're also like well it not now but the
there's so many festivals that just mmm
pop up fire festival yeah like like all
of that old that like anybody can make a
festival that's a black example like
yeah it'd be like you know like the
other other year
I was looking at that stuff to just see
what was happening around Oregon in the
summer and there was like the the what
they Eugene what the country fest of old
was a big country fair down their
country
oh yeah the organ country in the organ
isn't fair or the yeah I think it's the
organ country I can't remember off the
top of my head but that one and then
there there was like four they're like
small raves that happened out and like
the hood area coast like other music and
then there was that one that caused a
whole bunch of traffic over the hood
area that a couple years ago like the
illegal one yeah I I definitely went to
that well oh wait I was either friends
with the ones who did that one because
there was a lot of those going on around
here like gig sessions and stuff yeah
yeah I remember there being a one big
like illegal one that was kind of out
toward Eastern Oregon yeah and so there
was it's it's just to me it's like if if
you're gonna do the festival it's like
Coachella makes sense
mm-hmm where you have big artists
big-ass space multiple days like money
is dumped into that what yeah but if you
have like the touring festivals or like
other stuff like that it's kind of like
hey don't get me wrong
Ultra looks awesome right but it's like
what eight ultras yeah I know I know
it's want to go to like this Center one
I feel like good like the big one but I
I know I think an immersive festival is
so much different than so like what the
fest the effort organ that was way
different than EDC or Coachella I don't
know there's there's a lot of different
kind of festivals yeah I mean you only
that Burning Man the classic have you
done Burning Man no I am NOT a burner
not not a burner I are you know I've
never done it I think that like a couple
years ago I would have done it but now I
have this like everybody else does it so
I don't want to do it I'm like next
level trying to stay above the hipsters
I think I just don't want sand in my
urethra oh my god dude it it seems kind
of miserable in that aspect like I just
I just it feels like it's like cool you
once sand in every orifice of your body
and all on all your [__] and it don't
blow around yeah like I had to repair a
buddy of mine speaker that he brought
down to Burning Man in like
did you open to open it up and it's just
fill with dust like I feel like like a
Jumanji movie pretty much yeah you're
just like what how how did it get in
here this is the sealed box so going
back to team Banzai that's what you do
producing lies now it's kind of I was
like pointing out because I think for
non creators they don't really think
about it but it's almost like alter egos
you walk around with like I like I have
interviews on of like people in bands
people who are producers people who have
like companies people who are rappers
but they're like they're like oh I'm
coming to you as this name like my Mandy
but also unless I'm in this situation
I'm also team bonsai yeah like going
into different situations you kind of
have to plan it out as well so I think
before when I first started doing team
bonsai I treated it that way yeah and it
got really annoying and I felt like I
was a bit pompous where it's like well
I'm the artist blah blah blah blah blah
right and after working in recording
studio and stuff and dealing with many
different walks of life it's it's also
kind of like I've I've I've kind of
taken it back where it's like yeah I do
I do produce and I kind of keep it now
on the back length on the down low where
it's not like that's my main thing that
is what I that it's my identity because
there's a lot of users who do that let's
talk to it's like I'm a producer but
this is what I do but well like so
they're all about it and I I'm good on
you it's awesome but I also kind of like
cool there's a whole bunch of other [__]
that goes on that makes a person like me
right yeah and if you take that and put
it into your productions and it's like
awesome so a lot of my buddies who are
also producers like it seems like they
do it as a hobby but they're like hobby
also happens to make them money when
they do do it rather than like trying to
go for it as their only thing and not
succeeding we're like putting all their
eggs in one basket nice being a producer
because the reality of it is not
everyone's going to be able to make
money doing it right and if you are [__]
yeah yeah but that's the thing if you
can you can do like what you're doing
and feed into it it all feeds into
everything
you can utilize the skill set that comes
with producing for other stuff works
really well like I use my production
skills that when I have to when doing a
recording like oh hey maybe try playing
it differently or doing it this way and
maybe this is a bit more musical because
maybe which happens a lot people aren't
fully prepared when coming into the
studio so they're trying out a couple
different ideas that kind of thing
a few type beats you know that kind of
thing where you've got the lyrics
written but you've gotten a written to
five or six different beats so mm-hmm
we're gonna sing five or six different
versions of the song and see which one
sounds the best hey sometimes that's the
best way to get an idea how I sometimes
it's just having other people here it is
they're like oh dude number four was
like by far the best exactly exactly and
that's and that's one thing that I have
to stress to people who do come into the
studio cuz it's not all like you come in
you get an awesome thing right off the
bat like yeah you can come to a big
studio but if you're not putting down
awesome stuff to begin with or cool
stuff to begin with you're gonna get not
cool stuff coming out of it you just
that's that's what happens and so you
can only do so much studio magic and
when people come in and they're like
they don't have the option at home to
play back or they're not tech savvy
enough to like record on their phone
over the beat with their voice and have
that kind of instant feedback so they
can hear oh I actually need to be more
on time or oh I need to do this or oh
this does not sound good
like cuz it sounded way different in my
head that's usually the cases it's what
you hear in your head and what comes out
of your mouth are totally different
always yeah I feel like our life is just
trying to communicate what's in our head
to out here yes exactly
and then my part of my job is trying to
get what people what's in people's heads
out into a form that they can hear back
yeah when they're using just like
make it go boom yeah you're like what
yeah make it make it what make okay or
if they're or if they know a little bit
and they don't know the correct
terminology so they're trying to explain
something and it's like an an
explanation that I'd have no idea and
it's
that it's like oh you want a delay cool
that was my Bennett explanation to
explain an echo e-type sound that you
heard before right that kind of thing
yeah that's the communication this stuff
is so like it's such a language of its
own it's just like you know a
mathematician is gonna know a lot of
like birds around linear algebra and you
know physics stuff exactly they're gonna
be able to explain it in that way yeah
and so uses utilizing the production
side with the recording engineers side
like really does help and I suggest
anyone who is a producer or producing to
also look into the actual recording
engineer side because you'll be able to
make better sounding stuff that's the
one thing I see with a lot of younger
producers who are really talented like
they they can come up with really
[__] cool ideas and concepts sound
design and that kind of stuff but when
you hear their mix it's like this sounds
like [__] yeah like whoa like okay cool
I like how it's all written like what
sonically it sounds like just bad like
it sounds a MIDI I don't want to say
amateur
it just sounds you know thin no bass
right no like you can tell that it's
just they don't know how to mix so now
listen what to listen for and but they
know how to like create a song because
that's an entirely different realm yeah
writing and composing a song and
actually making it sound good two
entirely separate things yeah people
kind of need to realize with when you do
do a big studio type stuff or when you
do produce something is that you have to
really like spend the time doing all
that the pre stuff before you even come
into the studio because all the studio
does is make whatever ideas you have
into like a playback of old form right
and then you can use it you then you can
work with it and make it sound good and
mix it yeah it mix it and do all that
but you have to have the content first
and and that's that's one thing that it
seems has escaped a lot of people hmm
nowadays because of the instantaneous
instant gratification right like oh I
see my favorite artist doing this or oh
I just needed
load of beaten I can hop into the booth
and just go and it's like maybe you can
I have seen people do it and it's
impressive his [__] right but not
everyone is like that yeah you
definitely it's definitely a difference
when you get somebody who rolls in like
prepared it's definitely a different
vibe like I like it like you've had a
homey in here when I'm we've been in
here and it's just like alright I'm
ready I got these songs I got this
memorized I'm ready you ready like you
can just get so much more work done yeah
when you're and pee and you know what
you need to get done yeah I know what
you like are your end the goal is it's
not like a question mark like oh what
will we get done today it's like you
know we're getting this and this and
this done today right and I already know
what I have to say and and if you do
need to change something up it's usually
very minimal mm-hmm and so and that's
that's one thing is that you see a lot
of that nowadays compared to when I
started working with certain artists
they would be a lot more like ready to
go and then the big difference and that
is it's the how you people perceive the
end results and what like okay how they
perceive the end result and and they
don't have a concept of what actually
went in to get that end result just like
really what I'm trying to think of a
good example like the infomercial type
thing where you see the you see the end
result before like you see the whole
process to get the end result they're
like we've already done this before and
here it is right yeah I mean I kind of
get it with DJing when someone's like
I'm in the middle of you know something
at whatever bpm and I'm in this corner
of my mix and this key and I'm trying to
get to this vibe within thirty minutes
and then someone's like you play this
song right now like as they they just
see like the end outcome like all you do
is play music like someone you can't
come to Studio B like you just you put
my voice over and make it sounds yes
p.m. the bar just opened play the
beggars play the bangus yeah yeah
people's expectations are sometimes
fooled we have such a like there's the
bedroom producers is is such like a cool
interesting world now you know it's
really is an exciting thing like so many
cool things at people's fingertips like
you grew up
mess with all like this videotape stuff
and like converting this machine to this
thing with this sound and nowadays you
could just do that with a click of a
button yes no T's and plugins and now
just all digital it's also easy you also
have YouTube with all the [__] info
and a whole bunch of Miss info and
mm-hmm weird producers who are like if
you do it this way it's gonna sound like
this and it's like cool that's one of
five billion different ways to do it
okay but yeah that's one of the bigger
differences now is that it's it's you
have that kind of like instant knowledge
instant access to things that you didn't
before so that now people are like oh if
I want to do this I'll go on YouTube and
look up how to do it and that's how you
do it that's very well yeah again
nuanced you haven't you have different
methods and different things that when
you do branch out and actually start
working in this field if you want to
it's you you see a lot of things that
crossover a.k like from production and
DJing and like okay DJing you have you
have to deal with rhythms tempos and
getting body moving and stuff like that
with that you get like a good ear for
hearing things off time especially if
you're used to beat matching by without
hitting a sync button you can feel it
almost instantly when something is off
time right and then you have like the
technical side so I do a lot of IT work
and stuff and that's you have to be able
to set up a computer and be able to use
it that's a skill set that most everyone
should have in general nowadays but it's
it's stuff like that is it's a
culminating unlike a lot of other jobs
where it's like okay you do this you do
that it's you have to have a breadth of
skillsets and then shove it all into one
and use little bits and pieces when you
need to there's that's like most jobs
but with at least with this job I have
to take in facets from a whole bunch of
different subgenres so it's like taking
from different cultures pretty much to
you if you have to do a jazz album
alright
well they're not gonna want their kick
drum [__] slamming right in their
face like words no no
like maybe maybe some acid trials if
you're getting experimental by like in
the general there are standards and so
you have to like kind of go in with that
culture and that's your like take a
different facet of your life
take it take a different experience and
be like alright well this is a country
song okay
country music is like very vocal and
guitar heavy very tight very like well
performed if you listen to country very
rare in modern modern pop country you're
bad players right at all like very rare
and so you doing country it's like you
can't be as loose as you would like say
doing a grunge punk album and you have
to also remember that like okay there
who's gonna be listening to it who is
that who's the end result like there's
so many different like facets that go
into each individual genre that you have
to kind of remember and apply to
whatever you're working on right with
the DJing listen is so much [__]
different music helps a ton like you had
to listen to a bunch for your wedding
cuz you you wouldn't be playing the same
[__] at a wedding that you would be a
Saturday night bar yeah we're at a rave
or at a rave yeah like house party like
that's the thing is you really gotta
like that that's like I think the fun
part about when people like oh I want to
be a DJ or I want to be a producer like
they kind of forget that like enveloping
your whole life into it is like the fun
part like watching little YouTube videos
about this producer out of the way he
does this thing does correlate to the
wedding you're about to DJ next Saturday
like it all teaches you little different
things and you got to learn kind of
different like being able to like read
people and read situations too and kind
of like be able to show up as different
versions of yourself like I'm not going
to be the same guy playing techno on a
Saturday night as I am in a wedding
exactly
exactly get 100% it's the same like if
I'm going to act a little bit
differently with my crazy blunt smoking
clients then I will with my super
religious clients like that's just you
know that's just common kind of calm
since in a way but it also is a
necessity in certain genres and how you
vibe and get the end result right cuz if
you're in a room with a bunch of people
getting high and laying back and
chilling out and you're the sober
stickler like either caffeinated guy
that's your mix is probably not going to
reflect the vibe all right of the thing
and vice versa maybe like it's actually
huge it is maybe you're like a huge
stoner like I am yeah and you're gonna
be doing a session like I have coming up
in a bit which is probably going to be
some like very like classical strings
type stuff hmm I don't want to be
blasted out of my mind like I would for
a heavy hip-hop or trap session exact I
want to be like it's classical music
like the people who are listening to
this are not going well maybe they
they're probably not going to be on a
bunch of drugs like that's nice that's
the thing you got to put yourself in
like the listening yes you gotta like
yeah I have to change my hat so yeah
yeah go now to listener mode if I was
gonna just be listening to this in the
car what would I hear what would I not
like okay back to the engineer all right
you got to play this better or move your
to the mic now I'm mixing it okay cool
now I have to like is does it sound
correct as does this mix with this it
doesn't actually like feel right when
all the instruments come in and like
again these are super abridged things
it's much more involved than that but
it's that's kind of the mentality behind
it yeah and and having to be able to hop
between all those hats is like that
takes practice and not a lot of folk
have the option and ability to do that
and be like the patience to do that
because it's a time consuming and you
deal with a lot of really interesting
people along the way and that's what's
again like how you said you have to like
like that part of the job like you have
to be cool with that you can't be like
oh I have to had to work with this
problem
ya know you got to be like whoa I just
happen to work with this type of person
you know this type of person in this
type of person and because it's a much
more intimate one-on-one type of thing
almost like a tattoo artist not like a
doctor but almost like a tattoo artist
type of relationship yeah it's it's a
bit more intimate than just like going
somewhere and having like your mechanic
fix your car or having like this dude
build this for you yeah it's like you
you do exactly this yeah I you know yeah
like oh you repair computers yeah here's
my laptop fix it here's money thank you
it's like no I have to be sitting there
working back and forth with the person
because ultimately it's their thing in
the end it's not mine at all it's not
like I have a skill set that I build it
for them and then end of story I fix it
for them in the story I do fix things
but it's a different type of fixing it's
like taking their ideas and almost
fixing someone's ideas and fixing
someone's concepts which you don't do a
lot in other fields where you take an
idea and be like alright let's [__] with
it yeah you're the designer of the think
you listen to the words that I say in
this you use your hands to create what's
in another person's head exact times
like you've taken though hand I could
build the skills exactly and you have to
end a lot of times it's interpreting
really vague description okay
really really really that they they
don't realize is it vague at all until
you look at them and you're like yeah
until how would you set the deer and
headlights look like okay let's let's
see if this is what you want in most of
the time you could just work through it
and they're like that's it exactly
exactly and so the end that's part of
the fun of the job is like well I have
no idea what this person wants time to
start experimenting and that's what's
that's kind of exciting when you're like
well I have free rein to just kind of do
whatever I want with this song and see
how it goes and that's and that's what's
fun about it is you have that kind of
unknown like okay cool
I have a Play Doh to just play with hmm
but it's a song and it's not mine and
that's the other thing is it's a little
different is because it's not your song
a lot of times you're not like
emotionally invested so you make
decisions that are
way more broad and way more maybe not as
calculated per se for sure
but in general it becomes like that's at
least I do that's the vibe it's like oh
let's try this and see how this sounds
and if it doesn't work cool we'll try
something else
but you have to like it's kind of like
one of those you bit and that's you
build up a sound or a vibe for the
person with the person and that's it's
it's kind of a time-consuming process
because some people it comes really
quickly with others
other times you're pullin teeth and it
may never happen mm-hmm and sometimes
that's the case and and it it happens
but it's definitely part of the learning
period learning curve when you're like
oh I actually legitimately am not the
right fit for this person's work like
right had that I have had that happen
where it's like I'm sorry I am not the
right person to be the one working on
this because yeah you got to be able to
do that to you I don't know anything
about the genre all right I don't like
this daughter at all and I'm going to
charge you way more money because I'm
just having to deal with you and that
happens like remember how you act around
your engineers will get you perks and
fart because of you kind of a dick you
might you know charge you the dick fee
the dick fee
yeah and and and because we don't like
getting [__] around yeah dude it's a
different world it's not it's it's not
all cut and dry it's music it's it's art
and that's that's the thing that some
people forget is it's not like a doctor
yeah I liked what you said about tattoo
artists it's kind of like that
relationship yeah that's relatable for a
lot of people yeah and and it's it's
very similar cuz you're going to your
one guy who's really [__] good cuz he
knows how to do the art well he knows
how to get your ideas down and like
that's exactly what an audio engineer is
and turns the studio audio engineer and
producer is their job is to take the
ideas that are in your head make sure
that they're recorded and put down
they're actually good
mmm-hmm worth your time rather than like
you know a poor recording of an awesome
song which don't get me wrong if the
song is really that awesome a poor
recording sometimes gives it extra vibe
but this day and age it's that's a weird
thing to yeah it's just real yeah it's
just this day and age it's there's no
excuse you have such good options to get
a decent quality recording even just for
a demo at your house that like you
there's no excuse for what I hear a mix
that someone's done and it literally
sounds like a [__] mp3 from 2001
downloaded off of LimeWire that has been
already re-encoded three times 16 times
a different one time I got I had to play
the instrumentals for the outlaws who
their claim to fame was they're like to
pox cousins or something but they were
just like the worst quality sound files
they were like the thinnest waveforms
I've ever seen I was like how many times
did you read your own stuff off YouTube
and I only point that out because they
were totally [__] rude to me so I'm
just gonna but heard about it I guess
still so I do want to talk about team
bonsais creative process like so because
you've been doing like more modular
stuff too and yet really really stuff
one turn off all the nights step to get
more stoned I was listened to ADHD on
the way here like the the first song is
just a super good man I just imagine
yeah that one the first song like an
opening so that one was intended for
that specific purpose and then it just
kind of evolved into something else but
no that one that one was what did I do
again I got really stoned cuz a lot of
those are evolved like they start in one
direction and by the end by what I
release its you either an entirely
different song or if it's one of the
lucky ones it's done in a day like it
that's how my productions go it's I
their whole thing is just done like all
the ideas are just out I just blew my
load all over the Ableton and it's just
a mess it's pasted it's pasted and it's
just it's just white and goo everywhere
and then other times it's just it's just
dust going out and
bits at a time just blooms yep just purr
and and and they just barely coat like
an airbrush but do you save those ones
day yeah and those are but those ones
are like like that first song was one of
the dusts in like the first the first
bit the first half of the very
instrumental wide open he's sent these
stuff that one was all in a day and then
everything else was just incremental it
was like because it was like I heard I
heard the rest of it it kind of buildup
in my head but it wasn't one of those
like oh I got everything out like oh
cool I mean I've done other songs like
social media that one on there that one
was the whole beat and everything was
done in a day and that vocals are done
later like it's in my process a lot of
times as making the sounds first like I
will spend 3-4 hours just making sounds
and usually one sound or one bass line
or something like that will then spark
the entire song mmm and so that's how my
process has been lately is all I like
you said the modular stuff I have a
pretty decent sized modular system
eurorack modular synthesizer system the
kind you see like deadmau5 and those
guys like actual nubs the actual knobs
and Kate real what cables that I have to
plug in get things places and like and
so I'll use that to kind of make general
rhythms and other stuff like that like
just background noise a lot of times now
because I'll let that play and and come
up with kind of a pattern or rhythmic
kind of thing so I'm not just playing
off of a drum beat cuz I used to
literally just don't don't don't don't
don't don't don't don't and then record
whatever I ideas would come up and over
a four on the floor kick and it would
get boring and it's a good way to get
something down but it's a goodness after
you know five years of doing it that way
yeah because a lot of my stuff would
start off like I'd have a bass sound but
like a bass isn't like bass guitar bass
synth but like a bass level sound
then I would add the drums on top and
half the time I'm just being for the
for-loop to build off you just sucked
right back into it I get sucked right
back and do it which that's what happens
to a lot of producers but lately now
I've been right alike compose all the
instrumental parts or the general
instrumental parts first and then I will
do the drums because drums have now
become way too easy I mean like in terms
of like quickly throwing them out and
getting ideas and Michael rhythmic
patterns nothing basic and then when I
do like the weird rhythmic stuff that
takes time like weird
glitchy clicks that are totally off
tempo that they're off tempo yet on
tempo that kind of stuff yeah those take
time but like general just throwing out
an arrangement of drums for a 3-minute
song now is pretty like it after many
years of practice it's like alright cool
like I can get a general kind of rhythm
going and then adjust accordingly so a
lot of times now I'm just building the
song off of musical ideas or sound ideas
and kind of like vibes and like oh okay
like having this kind of like textural
ambient kind of thing and then it melds
into this or it's like just right off
the bat we're going drums bass
everything right right from the start
like I just did a full track which I'll
show you after oh yeah after we're done
with this power to Casting but none of
you listening you get to wait that's all
done with it Ableton's analog everything
everything but the master chained drums
since pads weird vocal sounding [__] all
of its done with Ableton to analog and
that was just to challenge myself to try
something different and make every
single sound using one set the one type
of synthesizer a very basic one and then
built-in plugins to actually make it
sound good and not sound like [__]
karaoke [__] from a Casio
giving yourself walls like that is
actually a really good idea like yes and
that use matter that's what I was gonna
go into which was like giving yourself
like there's there is a thing there's a
little bit of Zen of having those
limitations and that's what I kind of
like about hardware is that while I
[__] love
serum if you don't know serum is one of
the best synthesizers for PC Mac
whatever I don't think is on Linux but
PC and Mac and it is super powerful you
can do so much [__] with it you can
modulate and do tons of stuff it's
insanely powerful and sounds great well
with hardware you can't do that unless
you have a lot of [__] money right
like you can't just magically patch the
same thing to another thing with a cable
like you need a splitter and then more
cables and this and it's like oh cool
just to do what in serum is a
drag-and-drop motion cost you two
hundred and fifty dollars not even
kidding it can cost that much just for a
simple utility now it doesn't make sound
it doesn't do anything but when you have
a hardware synthesizer that's built so
that you have everything kind of like
routed for you like the korg ms-20 or
the the Mini Moke Model D or some of
those classic analog mono synths those
limitations lead you to me a bit more
like to be musically creative right you
got to work with what you got to work
with what you got and then and you kind
of kind of stick with it it's like oh
well I kind of wish that I can make this
this sound go a bit more like sharp in
the cut down so like the only the
technical term would be a very quick
envelope on like a filter and so it's
just like just shuts down well you only
have one envelope on it on most
synthesizers and sometimes two one for
volume and one for the filter but a lot
of times it's just one for both volume
and then maybe the filters so whatever
your volume settings that your filter
settings also at and you're stuck with
it there is no other way to change it so
that is your sound like you can't sound
design it and get it like really precise
it's that is yourself yeah working with
it yeah that's why you're working with
them then wouldn't you go back and
listen to old music that's how they
worked
that's how keyboardist and bands worked
is he bought a keyboard he bought it
because it was chock full of [__]
sounds you didn't have to actually
design yourself you just sat and played
and based your stuff off that and like
buying vinyl crates exactly and and you
would you it's like the yeah the Dilla
way you based
[__] hole beat off of one tiny little
fragment of a sample you found while
crate digging bless J Dilla oh yeah the
the the the way that Hardware you
interact with hardware without having a
screen and you're limiting those options
does give you the kind of the freedom to
like hey I'm gonna actually make some
music or make some weird noises or
something like that rather than spending
your time and clicking and focusing on
the actual act of doing the sound design
because that is a ton of fun in itself
but you don't really have anything
musical after you have a cool sound
right yeah it's hard to like keep going
yeah like to actually get like we're you
actually jamming and doing something and
so that's that's a that's a thing where
I've tried really hard to not get caught
in those loops while I produce where I
will I'll maybe either make a designated
day where hey today I'm just doing
random sound design like I'm making
kicks I'm making snares I'm making weird
bass patches I'm making pads maybe one
of those will inspire a song and a lot
of times that'll happen like all of a
sudden I made a cool last pad and a bass
oh well that's song that's gonna be a
song now or nothing happens and I'm
sitting there staring and Ableton like
everything sounds like [__] and you step
away and come back but a lot of times
it's to not get stuck in those sound
design loops it's like I'll make a sound
and then I will force myself to stop and
move on to the next one and not go back
to it until I have to like really focus
on it because otherwise I will spend 4
and a half hours listening to the same
bass loop making it a little bit better
a little bit better yeah oh no I wanted
to knock like this and then the minute I
add another sound hope it doesn't sound
right mm-hmm and so and and you lose
that kind of big picture mentality which
that's what and then you lose three
hours it yeah it sounds exactly the same
hours of listing dude dude sometimes
I'll get into just like making it just
like playing a synth or playing
something over and over just like
building sound design and then you'll
finally pause it and you're like your
body is like whoa like you like stop
sprinting through space you just felt
like you're like whatever frequency that
was just only
only way I can describe that is like the
same feeling you get when you take LSD
and you ride a bike
stop in the world the rubber bands
around you after you stop there's only
going to be a few a subset of listeners
who understand that reference but they
will know and they will be like oh my
god they're gonna make I'm getting into
sound design immediately like because
you were 100 percent right if you are
two and a half hours of jamming deep and
you just lost in the sauce
yeah you come back to reality you're
like what the [__] just happened where
did all the time what did I just do and
if if you're smart and your rear
according it you go back and listen you
go oh god what the [__] was I doing what
dimension was I on yeah yeah I I had a
time where I was I went to a concert
actually I went to a grandson show he's
the name of the artist but we were I had
working with sounds all day and I was
just feeling kind of wonky like my legs
just felt like wobbly like just because
I was doing a weird frequencies and
listening to binaural beats at some
point in the morning like in some of my
legs were literally wobbly at this
concert and I talked to my buddy I was
like bro we got to sit down I think my
legs feel like they're gonna whop wobble
off from this weird frequency I was
listenin to earlier today yeah that's
that's that's totally a thing like you
can totally get lost in the sauce would
just sound designing and that's what
happens but that's sometimes where you
stumble upon the coolest [__] when
you're just jamming for two hours and
all of a sudden you tweak one knob and
mm-hmm a whole song idea pops in your
head it's like I've had I had I had a
random like a random patch turn into an
entire song and the patch the whole song
is based around the same thing going
like like over and over again it evolves
throughout the things that's never the
same but that was literally just a
random like stoned [__] around that nip
like whoa what the what the hell is it
record right and and then it became a
song and it's that's the that's what I
like about like synthesizers in that
regard where you have that kind of
randomness and unlike a guitar or piano
or where you have to kind of have some
intent and some meaning fine it's very
rare that you can just start derping on
the piano or guitar without having some
sort of prior yeah you can't explain
whatever keys you want it's just like
this isn't fun I want to walk away yeah
exactly got a little bit with it with a
synthesizer you can set it to where it
generates kind of its own stuff
constantly randomly and and some people
might say that oh that that that's not
that takes no talent volleyball oh it
was like but it's it's it's a different
type of no talent it's like well yeah it
doesn't it's not like a skill set like a
guitar player a pianist or or any
classical musician but if you want to
actually get something cool that's
musical that's then that sounds
palatable and palatable it's a very
broad term it does take a bit of
know-how and knowledge and then and and
[__] around and technical knowledge to
be able to let the Machine [__] around
on its own right and know when to
interfere and when to interfere and how
to interfere yeah because I feel like
it's like you're I don't know you're
kind of like riding around you're kind
of constantly keeping track of your kind
of constantly keeping the beat like
keeping time I guess like even through
something where you're just like oh like
there's there's a time to it yeah you're
like looking for and you're like ready
to like as you're making your own beat
from the sound of nothing I think there
is still like a musical time to it yeah
and and that's that I mean that's
exactly what an oscillator is it's just
choose putting out a different you know
amount of oscillation over time the
quicker the the quicker the amount of
oscillation that's happening the higher
the pitch you perceive and so when
you're doing stuff with synthesizers
that's exactly what you're manipulating
is the the frequency of a wave form of
an electrical pulse that's then being
output to a speaker
that's like pure sound is what it the
way you could describe it is like the
purest type of sound you can get yes
there's no nothing else happening it's
just a single type of wave being drawn
in the electrons dude learning about
sound is so crazy like I was just I'm
constantly reminded of how just
mind-blowing it is like we just see that
like will you plug that into the wall
and it makes sound duh yeah it's like
always it's it's a whole bunch of really
complex waveforms and electronics
dancing around inside then reproduce
this so that we can actually hear it in
a correct way that doesn't sound [__]
up to us yes yeah it's an insane like
when you get to the technical like the
really nitty-gritty technical
mathematical nerdy [__] side of it it is
boring as [__] but also impressive as
[__] and there's many many smart people
that we built upon the shoulders of oh
definitely dude yeah definitely Tesla
for example Tesla coils but I mean like
[__] Bell mic yeah those guys who
helped invent you know telecommunication
and that kind of thing yeah it's not
incredibly impressive or anything no no
not at all just thinking about like the
amount of knowledge that I have in my
head cavity just like like if this all
went to [__] and then it's like I'm one
of the last ones and I'm like well Jake
you know the most about sound out of all
the people that are left can you remake
a speaker I'd be like what
yeah yeah I can make fart sounds my
mouth yeah exactly
Andy you do so we had met up we first
met through mentorship so thank you
teaching me I'm technically your student
or was yeah so how did you we just
briefly touch on that if you want how
did you get into to teaching and feel
like the teaching audio stuff was
because the awful company that we will
not name that we were both part of for a
while they were looking for people who
could teach Ableton and other stuff
because they had they just start
a program for Ableton Live and they were
originally doing I think Pro Tools maybe
logic but just Pro Tools and one of the
other engineers it works here was
teaching Pro Tools and they were like we
need people who teach Ableton so that's
how I started doing that with them and
actually like mentoring people as a job
and it started off pretty well it was a
different company back then
lots of ownership change of the loss of
yeah lots of different admin change and
I think of I think the concept though I
think I wanted to bring it up because I
think the the concept is so cool and
like it's the concept was really good
yeah and I mean I don't want to go I
can't like describe the concept lately
like giving it away at what we're
talking about just a different way of
teaching and learning yeah and just more
hands-on it had a much more hands-on
approach than normal and that was really
cool
mm-hmm but it had a lot of flaws in the
yeah no no me that it was executed on
their end right yeah but so I think on
the positive side of it for me like
again I went I went through my own
wringer with these people like I had a
whatever but being able to being able to
like come and learn face to face and
like if I'm working on something I can
like take my headphone off and ask you a
question yeah and it's it wasn't set up
in the sense that it was like the
typical classroom
yeah and that kind of thing which that
was that was nice and that's the best
way to learn in my opinion where you're
not like forced to write your this is
it's from this time to this time test is
on this time I'll see you then yeah it
just doesn't work for some people man
like it just I can't sit there and pay
attention for that one not at all
yeah I just I was just kind of I was
talking about it because I'm just kind
of curious with all this you know coming
back to the present time with all the
kovat sort of stuff like I feel like you
know all these kids are out of school
right now and they're we're discovering
different ways as a earth right now it's
a nation for sure but the whole world is
kind of learning new ways to learn
you know learning more like at home like
yeah the classrooms gonna be changing oh
yeah I have a feeling that online
classes and more remote worked and that
kind of stuff will probably become way
more normal
I have a feeling people are gonna
realize there's a lot of things we could
have been doing where we didn't have to
show up for [__]
meetings doc certain doctor's
appointments like what else um probably
like some government appointment type
stuff as well like stuff that can easily
be done remotely where you don't have to
stay in a waiting room and you have to
do it face to face and and notice how
much you know faster inefficient it is
when you don't have that layer of crap
to deal with like I kind of wish like
you know the DMV and like that kind of
[__] would would do that okay the DMV of
all places oh yeah like come on we like
understandable if you have to get your
photo taken for an ID and stuff but like
renewal forms and like that kind of [__]
like come on it seems like we should
that can be very easily automated yeah
with the incredible technology that we
were just talking about like we should
be able to figure out how to have
someone stand in front of a line and
take a photo for to get renew their
license yeah yeah or like yeah I'd let
you do it all online and then all you
have to do is just take a photo that's
it oh yeah that would be glorious
but yeah the I think I think one of the
biggest thing that's gonna probably
change is how like what the priority for
actually doing face-to-face stuff is
going to be like is it necessary now
that we have you know so much
telecommuting and other stuff like that
I mean how many people's jobs are you
know going to just be like oh there
there wasn't a Productivity dip when
they were working from home right there
are so many corporations and other
companies that were like no you can't
work from home you'll be a [__]
horrible employee oh well government
says you're working from home yeah in
sure enough they're gonna do the same
amount of work as money yeah and might
even do it better
you know there's not somebody over their
shoulder yeah but then other people
might you know like me included who when
you're at home it's like oh I don't
really feel like doing work not mom not
my workspace brain is not ready to work
I know you got a really that's a new
thing people are bringing out to start
learning how to like how to work from
home I actually had a homie who texted
me a couple hours ago he's like bro you
got to do like a video or something
about like mental health working from
home because like that's I'm all about
mental health and stuff and working from
home for a while like it's what's normal
to you and I like being able to set up
our zone and make sure this is right
before I go like we've built that up
over time there's all these people who
are like all clunky at home not knowing
what to do and not how to like they're
like well I'm gonna watch TV over here
now have to have a desk and wait I don't
actually have a workplace at home yeah I
don't have a workplace at home there is
no like desk or there is no designated
area no I'm like where we have that
option at our house because we've set it
up that way yes yeah like [__] you're
right you're 100% right there's so many
folks who are just thrown into the into
the fire just like well yeah you get to
now figure this [__] out you know who
not only don't want to but they're gonna
have to like learn how to do that anyway
so when you like you have learned a lot
from different facets in your life for
sure but I feel like I always like
putting a pin in this I'd be willing to
bet that you've probably learned a good
amount from YouTube and like reddit
forums and the internet oh my my faults
are true and that know you're wondering
percent true I mean with this job no
it's like a lot of others you're
learning you're learning a [__] it all
the time it's just with YouTube and and
whatnot
especially with YouTube there's a lot of
[__] to sift through for sure and
that's that and there didn't you there
used to be [__] but it didn't seem
to be as much so to say like I don't
want to say there were more reputable
outlets but they were more out there
were more out outlets that were better
at giving you more accurate information
that can be used in a broad spectrum
rather than a very nice like
make the best rap snare ever kind of
[__] or like really click baby stuff
right or like my biggest [__] pet
peeve I hate hate YouTube tutorials that
literally only play five to ten seconds
of whatever you're making for the entire
like 10-15 minute video you only ever
hear the end result like a tiny bit
you never hear and and during the whole
making of it's like they're explaining
everything but they're never playing
bits of like how it's going and they're
talking too much
yeah our heads need to know what the end
is yeah and so I've found a couple guys
who will do show what it is at the end
but they still talk too much right and
like there but that's the one thing is
it seems that people need to see the
thing happening without all the [__]
commentary mm-hmm because then your it
will click it was like oh this changes
this when that's what I try to tell all
of my former students and whatnot and
people who are wondering it's like
actually spend the time to like sit down
with the software or sit down with the
hardware little knobs [__] around with
it actually learn what's happening with
it like when you turn this knob what
does it do yes when you happen to turn
this knob and listen um at the same time
what what's the end result rather than
hopping into those YouTube tutorials
where they're like okay and then you go
here you use this and [__] throw this
saturator on and do the blah blah blah
and then it's like alright well so you
can follow along and follow along but
it's also like if you don't know how to
actually use step one and what the de
guy is doing and why he's doing it like
you can or what happens when you turn
that knob kind of like oh when I go
farther it makes it more high-pitched
squeegees squelchy sound squeegee that's
a good word in squelchy and squeegee and
squelchy
or like you turn this up and the the
tail end of the sound gets longer like
that kind of thing and and you if you
start building up how you interpret the
thing is happening
then when you see something going on and
you hear someone talking they might
explain it in a weird way that you're
like that's not how my brain interprets
a precise think it it makes it sound
like this in my head well when you're
watching a tutorial or something and
there's no one talking I'm just showing
you like with software and stuff you
just screen cap and you can see all the
mouse clicks and everything you don't
need an explanation why you can show
them like oh I'm turning this here's how
it sounds here's how it sounds it's like
that's what seems to be missing a lot
from a lot of toriel's is like the end
results how it sounds not like why you
did it or what you're doing it for it's
like no no that you can do that yeah you
can tell explain the concept but if
someone knows what the resonance of a
filter is you don't need to explain that
the whole [__] time I think yeah you
can you can get there themselves or you
can be like hey if you don't know what
these parts are here's a tutorial that
actually explains what everything is so
now when you watch this you're not going
in completely blind but I'm not going to
be explaining the goddamn reason each
and every [__] time right and so like
and I'll find that a lot where it's like
it's some of these I don't have any
examples and I don't want to give any
examples I don't want to bad-mouth
people and right off the bat there are a
couple I can think of but they will just
talk and talk and talk and that's it
it's like what what what is this
tutorial or is it I'm here to get
answers to my question here to try to
learn how you make this type synth or
whatever you titled it but in the end
it's like oh I got five minutes of
hearing this like wobble bass and then
over five seconds of hearing this wobble
bass and that's it like I heard how what
what you did to get to your end result
and none of the wire like how does it
sound in between these stages cuz a lot
of the times it's just they're hopping
okay and then you had this guy and then
you add this guy and then you add this
guy and it's just like okay that's cool
like good job in the sound design but I
kind of want to hear if maybe it sounded
different in stage 5 and it sounded like
better or what I was kind of going for
yeah and when you add this family why
does it sound like sound like that like
that kind of thing and like I said there
are guys who do do that and their
tutorials are pretty good but again
they's though
guys also try to or tend to explain
everything over again in each video and
that's where it's it's kind of like with
YouTube there's there are great
resources like previews like a pros
spectra Sound Studios like those guys
are really awesome and production expert
those guys are great but then you have a
bunch of these like the only way I can
describe the producers of the EDM era
sorry yeah well they just started in
like the the mid to late 2000s mhm and
it's like the FL maybe early Ableton
adopters but a lot of them are the FL
producers and stuff and you'll and ice a
lot of people just trying to mimic
sounds and that's that's the other thing
I was gonna get to which is like
everyone hears like [__] what's his
name really famous producer that I am
blanking on his name inter boom Metro
boomin thank you so you're thinking that
is literally who I was thinking uh-oh
because he's the one who's like I want
that member Metro boomin kick you right
I want that Metro boomin 808 right and
and or like I don't know if you go on
like the reddit that has a lot of kits
for drums on it yes but they there's so
many so many options that are all like
this is the kit from X and X song this
is the kit from X and X song and it's
just like cool I just want like a good
unique drum set that's like not you know
a direct rip from this dude I have a
song I think that people will find more
and more when they like do follow it cuz
those things when you see them like okay
so if I'm scrolling through and I see
like Kanye West drum kit like I like
Kanye West and so I have a pinch of like
oh that's cool but then you also gotta
be like but what can I really do with
that like exactly if you can't really
get to where you're gonna like improve
it or be able to use it or like you're
not really trying to recreate what he's
doing like you you want to sit down and
create something of your own exactly and
and like if you also if you take one of
those drum sets
you use it like it's just kind of like
okay well he just stole a different
producers like drum sound like we went
out and and I've heard I've heard
something like they just ripped the
entire kit like that they just used the
entire kit and you're like that's that's
the same sample from a nice Iraqis song
or like like that kind of stuff and
we're just like wait oh they downloaded
the unofficial drum kit and they're just
literally using that as their main drum
which I mean is cool I guess it's like
it's cool to do that and then you get
something going and you like get you and
your homies so like have fun it sounds
familiar and stuff but I don't know it's
just kind of like if your end goal is
trying to like get your own sound out or
sell later yeah like especially if you
sell it yeah at that point it's like
that's that's kind of a dick yeah dude I
think the the YouTube thing is huge for
me because that's something that like I
feel like the last I don't know a year
and a half or so I hate because I've
always been a YouTube guy and I'm always
like watching ton Z when I first started
producing pretty much just like have it
open on this window and then follow
along exactly on the right side and it
was just like I mean that's how I
learned at first but it held me back
what I should have been doing is just
like kind of learning how or what this
little corner of the thing needs you and
then just playing with them and
listening to it exactly seeing what that
sounds like and then if it sounds cool
do something else that sounds that same
sort of you know dig into it explore the
program I think that's we get really
caught up in watching tutorials and kind
of what failure the started result
I need that it's right or even opposite
just like thinking that you need to be a
professional before you make anything oh
yeah that's got to be the perfect sound
designer before you can even start
[__] around they'd do that to myself
very much that is the bane of so many
people's radical attempts is just I have
to be on the level of the weekend I have
to be on the level of [__] Celine
Dion I have to be on the level of
[__] whoever the [__] just make
some [__] bro [__]
yeah just make some [__] make some [__]
even if it's [__] yeah even it just put
it out yeah put it out because you won't
get anywhere if you don't write like
that's that's the whole point of making
this and doing this is like you make it
you put it out you let people hear it
there's some like it some won't you
might not like it yeah but you did
something bleep created it I probably
felt cool when you were learning it and
you can develop your whole life into it
dude just actly
just lean lean into what you enjoy and
just do it and then if people like it
they do and if they don't that's fine if
you like it hell yeah yeah that's
probably a good note to end on then yeah
I wanna so on the last thing to end on
I'm gonna ask you this one question and
we'll end on your answer all right if
aliens they roll on down they break
through the atmosphere and they're like
alright we only speak in sound so give
us your best musician and they happen to
go right outside here and they're asking
you this question so you have to be like
[__] I have to choose the musician or
person to communicate with these aliens
on behalf of planet Earth who would you
choose on behalf of planet behalf of
planet Earth and somehow these are weird
aliens that like only communicate with
sound waves and cool [__] so keep that
in mind do they have to be alive no okay
that changes things yeah you can
resurrect them in this scenario that's
that's a good that's a good question
that's a tough one
yeah it's there's there's what do you
think like more like like EDM guys or do
you think like producers like Jimi
Hendrix sort of guys like who are just
like legend or technical in terms of in
terms of sound or music like sound like
sound like sounds so or musician cuz I'm
thinking like cuz I can go a couple ways
like you can you go either way I'm
leaving it totally okay totally open oh
man
see if it was just sounds no words no
lyrics no lyrical content nothing like
that I would probably have to say
Vangelis okay
I'm drawing a blank they compose her for
Blade Runner okay okay okay
only because his sound design is [__]
amazing
no offense hans zimmer Vangelis has got
you beat if there were words that needed
to be said
probably Elton John ooh I feel that
probably if there were words probably
Elton John mm-hmm if there were it's
it's either Elton John or Freddie
Mercury like cuz no John alive so he'd
still be able to do [__] but French but
forward but yeah for no words Vangelis
hands down
cool yeah I think I think all three of
those are like if you had to resurrect
one to Freddie Mercury that's good too
yeah solid yep that's yeah it's a good
place to end it on it's a good place in
all right man I appreciate it thanks for
coming and BS and thanks for uh fighting
through the kovat oh yeah in this coma
we braved we braved the plague yes
brave - the plague all right listen er
take care of yourself
wash your hands like ten times and
listen to some good music check out team
Banzai on Spotify that's